Sampson County CR.087
State Archives of North Carolina
Sampson County
CR.087
287
Sampson County (N.C.)
State Archives of North Carolina
Clerk of Superior Court, Register of Deeds
Scope and Content
Sampson County was established in 1784 from Duplin County. Some early court records are missing. Partial causes may have been the actions of Federal sympathizers in 1865 and a clerk's office fire in 1921.
The deed books of Duplin County prior to 1784 are among the records of Sampson County.
Sampson County (N.C.). County/District Health Departments.; Sampson County (N.C.). Register of Deeds.; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
Sampson County (N.C.)
- Bonds, Licenses, Oaths, and Registrations, 1834-1924; CR.087.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  Scope and Content
  This series may include Apprentice Bonds, Bastardy Bonds, Official Bonds and Records of county officials, Oaths taken by county officials, and other miscellaneous bonds and records pertaining to legal responsibilities of service granted through the courts, as well as Assumed Business Names, Corporations, and Partnerships and Brands or Marks registered in the county and Licenses and Registrations of merchants and professionals kept by the county.
  - Bastardy Bonds and Records, 1835-1924; CR.087.102; 287.2; 287.2.1; CR.087.102.1- CR.087.102.2; Bonds (legal records); Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Bastardy Bonds and Records)
    Arrangement
    Chronological
    Includes volumes and boxes of bastardy bonds, arranged chronologically. Other papers may include presentments against and examinations of unwed mothers and mothers-to-be, warrants to bring the putative fathers to court, and receipts for payments made on behalf of bastard children.
  - Official Oaths, Records of [Microfilm], C.087.10000; 350; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Official Oaths, Records of)
  - Corporations, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.10000; 8; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Corporations, Record of)
  - Corporations, Partnerships, & Assumed Names, [Microfilm], C.087.10000; 114; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Corporations, Partnerships, & Assumed Names,)
  - Index to Partnerships and Assumed Names [Microfilm], C.087.10000; 115; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Index to Partnerships and Assumed Names)
- County Administration, 1785-1852; CR.087.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.
  Records pertaining to or created by the administrative bodies of the county, including but not limited to the county Board of Commissioners, Board of Education, Board of Health. May includes County Accounts and Claims, Journals and Ledgers of County Officials, and/or Records of Wardens of the Poor, as well as record documenting county boundaries and changes thereto.
  See series 1, Bonds, Licenses, Oaths, and Registrations, for Oaths of county officials, and series 3, Court Records, for other records pertaining to county administration, if available.
  - County Accounts and Claims, 1828-1852; CR.087.910; 287.85; 287.85.1; CR.087.910.1; Accounts; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item County Claims Allowed)
    Records pertaining to accounts and claims against the county for services rendered. Volumes include County Claim Allowed.
  - Records of the Wardens of the Poor, 1785-1824; CR.087.927; 287.102; 287.102.1; CR.087.927.1; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Minutes of the Wardens of the Poor (Vestry Minutes))
    Records concerning the care of the poor and infirm, a function of the counties before it was assumed by the State Board of Charities and Public Welfare in 1917. In colonial times, care for the poor was an ecclesiastical responsibility; records from this period may be found in vestry minutes. From 1777 to 1868, maintenance of the unfortunate was entrusted to the Wardens of the Poor; after 1868, the Board of County Commissioners assumed the responsibility. Volumes may include vestry minutes, minutes and accounts of the Wardens of the Poor, accounts and registers of the county home, and accounts of outside poor (impoverished persons living at home rather than in the county home).
    Other terms for these records: Parish Books or Parish Accounts.
  - Minutes, Board of County Commissioners [Microfilm], C.087.20000; 9; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Board of County Commissioners)
  - Minutes, Board of Education [Microfilm], C.087.20000; 119; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Minutes, Board of Education)
  - Warden of the Poor, Record of [Microfilm], C.087.20000; 239; Sampson County (N.C.) (Reel Warden of the Poor, Record of)
- Court Records, 1784-1968; CR.087.3; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
  Biographical/Historical
  County Courts of Pleas and Quarter Sessions evolved from precinct courts in 1738. The courts were composed of three or more Justices of the Peace and sat four times each year. The functions of county courts may be categorized into three distinct areas-judicial, probate and administrative-that are reflected in the minute dockets. The courts exercised both civil and criminal jurisdiction, original and appellate (from magistrates courts). Probate responsibilities included acknowledgment and probate of deeds; probate of wills; appointment and qualification of administrators, executors and guardians; binding of apprentices; and inquisitions of lunacy. The court also served as the governing body of the county, responsible for the appointment and qualification of local officials, levying of local taxes, expenditure of public funds, granting of licenses (tavern keepers, ferry operators, and peddlers), registration of stock marks, paternity inquisitions, and emancipation and manumission of slaves.
  Courts of Pleas and Quarter Sessions were abolished by the Constitution of 1868. The judicial functions devolved to county Superior Courts and Justices of the Peace Courts; the probate function was vested in the clerk of Superior Court; and administrative responsibilities were inherited by the newly created Boards of County Commissioners. Superior Courts were established in each county in 1806, replacing the district superior courts that had functioned since 1778. Originally, the county Superior Court sat twice each year, spring and fall terms, with six judges riding circuit. Each county had separate clerks for Law and for Equity. These courts had original and appellate civil and criminal jurisdiction, as well as jurisdiction over actions in equity. Criminal jurisdiction extended to serious felonies, such as murder, rape, larceny, house breaking, assault and battery, riot, and forgery; civil jurisdiction extended to suits involving $100 or more (after 1868, $200 or more). Other matters assigned to Superior Court included legitimization of bastards, emancipation and manumission of slaves, registration of aliens, and hearing of grand jury presentments and reports. Later, matters handled before a clerk were classified in Special Proceedings and Orders and Decrees, which included things such as adoptions, name changes, incompetency hearings, and many estate and guardian matters.
  This series includes records pertaining to the administration and actions of the county court system, particularly Civil and Criminal Actions before a jury and other actions before the court or the clerk, such as Special Proceedings. The dominant court prior to 1868 was known as the Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; after court reform circa 1868, it was known as the Superior Court.
  For court records concerning land and property matters, see also series 4, Land and Property Records. For records pertaining to Wills and Estate matters, see also series 5, Estates Records and Wills. For Adoptions, see also series 6, Marriage, Divorce and Vital Statistics. Series 10, subseries 928, may also contain loose court records.
  - Minute Dockets, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions and Superior Court, 1794-1968; CR.087.MD; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    The minute dockets record the daily transactions of the court, generally recording judgments in civil and criminal actions or documenting non-juried matters. They also reflect the internal workings of the court, recording the appointment and qualification of clerks, the summoning and impaneling of juries, and the hearing of grand jury reports.
    - Minute Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1794-1868; CR.087.301; 287.6; 287.6.1; CR.087.301.1- CR.087.301.15; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Minute Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
      Includes volumes spanning the following dates: 1794-1799 1800-1808 1808-1813 1813-1818 1818-1824 1824-1830 1830-1835 1835-1839 1839-1843 1843-1846 1846-1851 1851-1857 1858-1865 1865-1866 1866-1868
    - Minutes Dockets, Superior Court, 1814-1968; CR.087.311; 2003.8.54; 287.16; 287.16.1; CR.087.311.1- CR.087.311.29; CR.087.311.30 - CR.087.311.36; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Minutes Dockets, Superior Court)
      Clerk of Superior Court
    - Equity Minute Docket, Superior Court, 1807-1868; CR.087.314; 287.19; 287.19.1; CR.087.314.1- CR.087.314.2; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Equity Minute Docket, Superior Court)
      Minutes of the Superior Court of Law and Equity (1806-1868).
  - Appearance and Reference Dockets, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions and Superior Court, 1821-1868; CR.087.AR; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.
    Records include Appearance Dockets for the Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions and Superior Court, which list civil cases to appear for any other purpose than jury trial, including preliminary proceedings, and document issuance of writs, summonses, and subpoenas as well as appeals from lower courts and proceedings by petition. Dockets show names of parties, nature of action, and summaries of pleadings or proceedings. Later Appearance Dockets usually were merely lists of persons bonded or otherwise held to appear before court in criminal matters, including persons on probation and material witnesses.
    Prior to 1820, both Appearance Dockets and Reference Dockets were often kept in same volume with Trial Dockets, which are listed in subseries CV, Civil Dockets, if available.
    - Appearance Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1821-1868; CR.087.303; 287.8; 287.8.1; CR.087.303.1- CR.087.303.4; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Appearance Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
      Record of issuance of writs, summonses and subpoenas to bring defendants and witnesses to following term of court. Also records appearances of appeals from magistrates' courts and of proceedings by petition (sometimes recorded in separate Petitions Docket). Columnar arrangement shows number of case and name or initials of attorneys; names of parties; form of action; disposition of writ; and any rule or action taken by court at term, including confessed judgments. Prior to 1820, appearance dockets were often kept in same volume with trial dockets.
      Volumes span the following dates: 1821-1833 1833-1842 1853-1861 1861-1868
    - Appearance Docket, Superior Court, 1858-1868; CR.087.313; 287.18; 287.18.1; CR.087.313.1; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Appearance Docket, Superior Court)
      Record of issuance of writs, summonses and subpoenas to bring defendants and witnesses to following term of court. Also records appearances of appeals from lower courts and of proceedings by petition (sometimes recorded in separate Petitions Docket). Columnar arrangement shows number of case and name or initials of attorneys; names of parties; form of action; disposition of writ; and any rule or action taken by court at term, including confessed judgments. After 1868, the functions of the appearance docket were continued with some modifications in the Summons Docket.
  - Judgment/Execution Dockets, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions and Superior Court, 1800-1946; CR.087.JE; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Equity Execution Dockets and Execution Dockets record the names of all parties involved in compensatory judgments awarded by the Court of Equity or Superior Court. Information includes names of parties to action; nature of action; amount of judgment; bill of costs; type of writ issued, its execution; satisfaction of judgment, in the case of Equity Execution Dockets; and sheriff's return. After 1868, in most counties this information was recorded in Judgment Dockets, although some continued to use separate Execution Dockets.
    - Execution Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1800-1814, 1831-1868; CR.087.304; 287.9; 287.9.1; CR.087.304.1- CR.087.304.4; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Execution Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
      Record of money due to successful litigant, fines and court costs; the type of recovery writ issued; and the execution of writ and satisfaction of judgment.
    - Equity Execution Docket, Superior Court, 1823-1868; CR.087.316; 287.21; 287.21.1; CR.087.316.1- CR.087.316.2; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Equity Execution Docket, Superior Court)
      Record of money due to successful litigant in actions at equity, fines and court costs; the type of recovery writ issued; and the execution of writ and satisfaction of judgment.
    - Execution Docket, Superior Court, 1819-1946; CR.087.318; 287.23; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
      Record of money due to successful litigant, fines and court costs; the type of writ issued to recover same; and the execution of writ and satisfaction of judgment. After 1868, in most counties this information was recorded in Judgment Dockets, although some continued to use separate Execution Dockets.
      - Execution Docket, Superior Court, 1819-1832, 1858-1869; CR.087.318; 287.23.1; CR.087.318.1- CR.087.318.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Execution Docket, Superior Court)
      - Judgment Docket, Superior Court, 1867-1946; CR.087.318; 2003.4.27; 287.23.2; CR.087.318.3- CR.087.318.44; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Judgment Docket, Superior Court)
        Volumes CR.087.318.30 (1929-1949) and CR.087.318.31 (1943) also include land tax sales records.
      - Index to Judgments, Superior Court, 1868-1877; CR.087.324; 287.29.1; CR.087.324.1; Indexes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Index to Judgments, Superior Court)
        Transfered out (from us)
  - Civil Dockets, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions and Superior Court, 1784-1927; CR.087.CV; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Record of civil causes expected to come to trial during term. Brings forward information from Appearance Docket and also shows pleadings of defendant, prior to ruling by court, verdict, judgment, and final orders. In most counties prior to 1820, Appearance, Trial, and Reference Dockets were maintained in one civil docket at the convenience of the clerk. With the proliferation of cases after 1820, most clerks began keeping the various civil dockets in separate volumes. After 1868, this information was recorded in Civil Issues Dockets, including names of parties, history of cases carried forward from Summons Docket, and note of proceedings at trial. See also series AR, Appearance and Reference Docket.
    - Trial Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1784-1868; CR.087.308; 287.13; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.
      - Trial and Appearance Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1784-1791, 1808-1814; CR.087.308; 287.13.1; CR.087.308.1- CR.087.308.2; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Trial and Appearance Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
        Volumes span the following dates: 1784-1791 (includes Reference Docket) 1808-1814
      - Trial Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1820-1868; CR.087.308; 287.13.2; CR.087.308.3- CR.087.308.9; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Trial Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
    - Equity Trial Docket, Superior Court, 1816-1862; CR.087.317; 287.22; 287.22.1; CR.087.317.1- CR.087.317.2; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Equity Trial Docket, Superior Court)
      Record of equity actions expected to come to trial during term. Brings forward information from appearance docket and also shows pleadings of defendant, prior ruling by court, judgment, and final orders. May include Equity Appearance Docket in same volume or in a separate book.
    - Trial Docket, Superior Court, 1809-1925; CR.087.322; 287.27; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
      - Trial and Appearance Docket, Superior Court, 1809-1831; CR.087.322; 287.27.1; CR.087.322.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item Trial and Appearance Docket, Superior Court)
      - Trial Docket, Superior Court, 1845-1869; CR.087.322; 287.27.2; CR.087.322.2- CR.087.322.3; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Trial Docket, Superior Court)
      - Civil Issues Docket, Superior Court, 1869-1925; CR.087.322; 287.27.3; CR.087.322.4- CR.087.322.10; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Civil Issues Docket, Superior Court)
      - Cross Index to Civil Issues Docket, Superior Court, undated; CR.087.324; 2004.3.18; 287.29.2; CR.087.324.3; Indexes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Cross Index to Civil Issues Docket, Superior Court)
    - Records of Assignees, Receivers and Trustees, 1856-1927; CR.087.929; 287.104; 287.104.1; CR.087.929.1- CR.087.929.5; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Records of Assignees, Trustees, and Receivers)
      Box C.R.087.929.2 contains records relating to the Clinton Loan Association, 1892-1907, including an 1882 map of the town of Clinton, with a key to dwellings and inhabitants.)
      Includes boxes of records concerning assignees, receivers and trustees appointed to settle the financial affairs of bankrupt individuals and businesses. In some counties, the records are merged into one chronological series; in others, the records of the three types of agents have been separated. Also includes volumes of accounts of assignees, receivers and trustees.
  - Civil Action Papers, 1790-1960; CR.087.325; 287.30; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Civil case files from magistrates courts, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, Superior Court, and, in some counties, other inferior courts. In most counties, also contains executions issued supplementary to civil judgments. Civil actions concerning are filed separately.
    See also Court Records subseries 328, Executions; series 10, Miscellaneous Records, subseries 924, Personal Accounts, for merchant account related to bankruptcy filings; and/or series 10, subseries 928, Miscellaneous Records, for loose civil case files, if available.
    - Civil Action Papers, 1790-1924, 1927-1960; CR.087.325; 2017.6.100; 287.30.1; CR.087.325.1- CR.087.325.20; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Civil Action Papers, Box Unprocessed Civil Actions, Judgments #4411-21652, Box Unprocessed Civil Actions, #21653-21732, Box Unprocessed Civil Actions, #100-2226)
      Chronological (processed); file number (unprocessed)
      Processed criminal action papers (1790-1924) are arranged in chronological order and housed in 20 fibredex boxes numbered CR.087.325.1- CR.087.325.20.
      Unprocessed criminal action papers, files #100-2,226 and #4,411-21,732 (1927-1960), are in roughly file number order and housed in 65 letter boxes.
    - Civil Action Papers Concerning Land, 1791-1932, no date; CR.087.325; 287.30.2; CR.087.325.21- CR.087.325.33; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Civil Action Papers Concerning Land)
  - Criminal Dockets, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1806-1968; CR.087.CR; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Trials in criminal court were recorded in Crown Dockets in the colonial period, State Dockets from the colonial period to 1868, and Criminal Docket; Criminal Issues Docket; or Judgment Docket, State Cases, post-1868.
    - State Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1806-1868; CR.087.307; 287.12; 287.12.1; CR.087.307.1- CR.087.307.7; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item State Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
      Criminal docket tracking appearance and trial of state prosecutions. During the colonial period, known as Crown Docket.
    - State Docket, Superior Court, 1832-1968; CR.087.321; 287.26; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
      Criminal docket tracking appearance and trial of state prosecutions. After 1868, known as Criminal Issues Docket.
      - State Docket, Superior Court, 1832-1868; CR.087.321; 287.26.1; CR.087.321.1- CR.087.321.3; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions. (Item State Docket, Superior Court)
      - Criminal Issues Docket, Superior Court, 1868-1968; CR.087.321; 2003.4.27; 287.26.2; CR.087.321.3.1 - CR.087.321.11; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Criminal Issues Docket, Superior Court)
        There are no records for 1886-1903 and 1918-1923.
  - Criminal Action Papers, 1823-1934; CR.087.326; 2017.6.101; 287.31; 287.31.1; CR.087.326.1- CR.087.326.26; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Box Criminal Action Papers, Box Unprocessed Criminal Papers)
    Chronological (processed); alphabetical (unprocessed)
    Processed criminal action papers (1823-1934) are arranged in chronological order and housed in 25 fibredex boxes numbered CR.087.326.1- CR.087.326.26. Unprocessed criminal action papers are in roughly alphabetical order and housed in 15 letter boxes.
    Criminal case files from magistrates courts, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, Superior Court, and, in some counties, other inferior courts, usually arranged chronologically. In most counties, records also include executions issued supplementary to criminal actions. Series 10, subseries 928, Miscellaneous Records, may also include loose criminal actions.
  - Clerk's Minute Docket, Superior Court, 1925-1931; CR.087.324; 287.29; 287.29.3; CR.087.324.2; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Clerk's Minute Docket, Superior Court)
    Miscellaneous dockets include clerk's minute docket (not special proceedings).
  - Minute Dockets, Other Courts, 1881-1968; CR.087.331; 287.34; Minutes; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Includes minute dockets from various inferior courts which were operational at times between the court reforms of 1868 and 1965, such as Criminal Court (in Craven, Mecklenburg, New Hanover and Wake counties), Inferior Court (1877-1885), Circuit Criminal Courts (reconstituted as Eastern/Western District Criminal Courts, 1895-1901), Recorders Court (1900-1970), and General County Court (1923-1970).
    - Minute Docket, Inferior Court, 1881-1885; CR.087.331; 287.34.1; CR.087.331.1; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Minute Docket, Inferior Court)
    - Minutes [Docket], Recorders Court, 1952-1957; CR.087.331; 2004.9.59; 287.34.2; CR.087.331.2 - CR.087.331.3; Dockets; Sampson County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court. (Item Minutes [Docket], Recorders Court)